{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man is the subject of a biography by Robert Wilson subtitled “An American Life,\" and this man funded a series of renovation projects in Connecticut that were part of his “profitable philanthropy.” This man once testified against William Mumler, who was considered a “spirit photographer.” This businessman once offered to provide $500 to anyone who could demonstrate the ability to speak with the dead and became known as the prince of the “humbug\" hoax. Claiming “a sucker is born every minute,\" for ten points, who was this businessman who founded a circus with James Anthony Bailey?",
      "answer": [
        "Phineas Taylor Barnum or P.T. Barnum",
        "Barnum and Bailey"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person expressed their appreciation for Cox’s Orange Pippin apples and Wensleydale cheese in the essay In Defence of English Cooking. One book by this author notes that mining households spend only \"ten pence a week on green vegetables and ten pence half-penny on milk..., and nothing on fruit.\" That book by this author was written after studying the working class in Lancashire and Yorkshire. For ten points, name this English author of The Road to Wigan Pier who coined authoritarian psychology terms like \"thoughtcrime\" and \"doublethink\" in the novel 1984.",
      "answer": "George Orwell or Eric Arthur Blair"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body of water was described by António Galvão as a “dragon’s tail.” Philip Parker King spent five years surveying the area surrounding this body of water, and for thousands of years, indigenous groups, such as the Kawésqar, inhabited this body of water. The Treaty of Peace and Friendship of 1984 between two bordering countries recognized this body of water as a demilitarized zone. For ten points, what \"Strait\" on the southern tip of South America is named for a Portuguese explorer?",
      "answer": [
        "Straits of Magellan or Estrecho de Magallanes",
        "Estrecho de Todos los Santos",
        "Straits of All Saints before \"explorer\" is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Carlos Salinas's tenure as president of this company included the arrest of the union boss José Hernández Galicia, who was using violent force to coerce the syndicates of workers. Following the creation of this company, former Secretary of Agriculture Saturnino Cedillo [[seh-DEE-yoh]] declared the sitting government illegitimate and revolted from his power base. Citing Article 27 of the Constitution of 1917, Lázaro Cárdenas ordered the creation of this company after seizing Anglo-Dutch and American holdings. The national oil company of Mexico is, for ten points, what state enterprise created in the 1930s?",
      "answer": [
        "PEMEX",
        "Petróleos Mexicanos 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As the head of Charles University, this man affirmed his nation's neutrality in the Western Schism. This man is credited with developing a dot above a diacritic which later became the háček [[HAH-chek]] for a language he helped to codify in his Orthographia bohemica. While he believed in transubstantiation, this man was heavily influenced by John Wycliffe and was condemned as a heretic at the Council of Constance. For ten points, name this Bohemian theologian who was burned at the stake and names a series of wars with the Holy Roman Empire fought after his death.",
      "answer": [
        "Jan Hus or John Huss",
        "or John Hus",
        "Hussite",
        "or Hussite Wars"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a Supreme Court case, this treaty was deemed “useless” by Chief Justice James Pendergast. The similar Batman’s Treaty was signed in a nearby country five years before this treaty, in which over 500 representatives of one side were presented with a non- English version. In addition to working on its central country’s Declaration of Independence, James Busby helped draft this treaty with William Hobson. Negotiated in 1840 in a country containing Mount Cook, for ten points, what was this treaty through which lands were ceded by the Maori?",
      "answer": "Treaty of Waitangi ] or Te Tiriti o Waitangi"
    },
    {
      "question": "This campaign was announced with a tweet stating, “We must now realize the promise of America by trusting God, unifying our vision and building our future.” Over 600 petition signatures from this campaign were claimed to be fraudulent due to “nearly identical handwriting and others [lacking] complete addresses.” Michelle Tidball, a preacher from Wyoming, was selected to be the running mate for this campaign's candidate. For ten points, what campaign for the Birthday Party was announced by a Chicago rapper to run for president of the United States?",
      "answer": [
        "Kanye West 2020 presidential campaign",
        "either Kanye",
        "West",
        "Ye for President",
        "obvious equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man narrowly avoided the same fate as Elijah Lovejoy at a speech given by George Thompson. A faction led by Lewis Tappan split off from this man’s organization over the election of Abby Kelley. This leader publicly burned a copy of the Constitution in protest, calling it “a covenant of death.” This man was a close ally of Wendell Phillips, who succeeded him as president of the American Anti-Slavery Society. For ten points, name this fierce abolitionist and orator who published The Liberator.",
      "answer": "William Lloyd Garrison 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "The last person to receive this award was Hayley Mills for her performance in the 1960 film Pollyanna. This award was established after Jackie Cooper’s performance in the film Skippy lost to Lionel Barrymore. Bob Hope called this award the “Oscarette” when presenting it to Margaret O’Brien. First won by Shirley Temple in 1934, for ten points, what now-discontinued award recognized child actors and actresses for their performances in film?",
      "answer": [
        "Academy Juvenile Award",
        "Juvenile Oscar",
        "Juvenile Academy Award",
        "Oscarette before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In reference to this politician, a billionaire once said, “Please don’t call the manager on me.” This politician claimed that a certain quality “has been part of my story, I guess, since the day I was born.\" Elon Musk once compared this politician to his “friend’s angry mom” and referred to her as “Karen” while noting his high tax contributions. During his first presidential campaign, Donald Trump repeatedly called this woman “Pocahontas” in reference to her claims of being part-Native American. For ten points, name this progressive Democratic Massachusetts senator.",
      "answer": [
        "Elizabeth Warren or Elizabeth Ann Warren",
        "Elizabeth Ann Herring 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1990s, an activist group made up of employees of this company known as Fuerza Unida [[FWEHR-zah oo-NEE-dah]] led a campaign against it for higher pay. A Latvian immigrant, named Jacob Davis, co-founded this company and came up with a patent to utilize copper rivets. Overalls began to be sold by this business in the 1870s, a few decades after its namesake founder originally operated a business on 90 Sacramento Street in a city where miners flocked during the California Gold Rush. Denim is heavily utilized by, for ten points, what company, the first to manufacture blue jeans?",
        "answer": "Levi Strauss & Co. or Levi’s"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before partnering with Levi Strauss, Jacob Davis, the inventor of modern jeans, operated a tailoring business in what \"Biggest Little City in the World\" in Nevada?",
        "answer": "Reno, Nevada"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Project FUBELT aimed to prevent this man from ascending to power. This man attained his highest office by obtaining a plurality vote over Jorge Alessandri as a candidate for the Popular Unity Coalition. This man appointed general Carlos Prats to the cabinet as his Minister of the Interior. This man gave his last speech while enemy troops were storming the La Moneda Palace and nationalized his country’s copper mines. For ten points, identify this Marxist president of Chile who was succeeded by Augusto Pinochet.",
        "answer": "Salvador Allende ] Gossens or Salvador Guillermo Allende Gossens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The CIA opposed Salvador Allende during Operation Condor, which also helped Alfredo Stroessner secure power in what country, where documents of his violent tactics were recorded in the \"Archives of Terror\"?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Paraguay or República del Paraguay",
          "or Tetã Paraguái"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "It's not Spain, but protests in this country erupted during the 1937 funerals of two supporters of Francisco Franco. The last living recipient of the Order of Victory was a leader of this country, who succeeded a non-Spanish Ferdinand I. During a 1941 massacre, this country was in control of Odessa. Michael I was a king of this country, another of whose leaders feuded with Horia Sima, the head of its Iron Guard. Once led by Ion Antonescu, for ten points, what is this European country governed from Bucharest?",
        "answer": [
          "Romania",
          "Kingdom of Romania"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "From 1948 to 1989, which organization served as the secret police of Communist Romania?",
        "answer": [
          "Securitate",
          "Departamentul Securității Statului",
          "Department of State Security"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following a defeat to this city state, Argia searched for the dead body of her husband then unsuccessfully tried to revive him with tears and kisses. The Nemean Games were founded while a group was en route to this city. Adrastus was the leader of the aforementioned group which aimed to restore a brother of Ismene and Antigone [[an-TIG- oh-nee]] to the throne of this city. The “Seven Against [this city]\" assisted one side in a conflict between the sons of an exiled king who married his mother. For ten points, name this Greek city-state legendarily ruled by Oedipus.",
        "answer": [
          "Thebes or Thíva",
          "or Thêbai"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Ancient Greek playwright documented the tragedy of Oedipus and wrote the plays Electra and Ajax?",
        "answer": "Sophocles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two members of this family were accompanied by the ambassador Koeketei on a trip in which a paiza was to be bestowed upon the pope. An outpost at Sandak on the Crimean Peninsula was established by the aforementioned brothers from this family whose nephew wrote about Manji in a work sometimes referred to as Il Milione [[ill-mill-YOH- neh]]. That member of this family lived during the 13th century and served in Kublai Khan’s court. For ten points, identify this family that included the Venetian traveler Marco.",
        "answer": [
          "Polo family",
          "Marco Polo",
          "acceptNiccolo Polo",
          "Maffeo Polo"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The name of the Khitan people inspired what archaic European term for Yuan China?",
        "answer": "Cathay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the War of 1812, Fort Howard was constructed on this body of water. A self- proclaimed Mormon king, named James Strang, reigned for six years on a major island within this body of water. The first European to visit this body of water was Jean Nicolet. Voyageurs led by the explorers Marquette and Jolliet followed this lake until reaching the Fox River near Green Bay. For ten points, name this Great Lake which saw a massive uptick in shipping with the growth of Chicago.",
        "answer": "Lake Michigan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A survey of Beaver Island overseen by James Strang in Lake Michigan was later published by this organization that operates museums in Washington, D.C.",
        "answer": "The Smithsonian Institution 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Manasseh Cutler helped secure Congressional support for this bill, after which a group called “the forty-eight” established a settlement at Marietta. Nathan Dane claimed to have authored the sixth article of this act which included a prohibition on slavery. A five- man government was to run this act’s central location while its population was under five thousand. A provision on natural rights in this act is thought to have influenced the Bill of Rights written two years later. For ten points, name this act which created a territory encompassing an area now including Indiana and Ohio.",
        "answer": "Northwest Ordinance of 1787"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In early discussions regarding the lands west of the Appalachians, Thomas Jefferson suggested creating ten rectangular states in the region, including states named Metropotamia, Washington, and this name. Taken from a Mohawk word, this name is most famously associated with a town in Upstate New York and a 1777 campaign which took place nearby.",
        "answer": [
          "Saratoga",
          "Saratoga Campaign",
          "Battles of Saratoga"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Shockley is often called the \"father of [this region]\" a result of his attempts to commercialize his transistor design. Frederick Terman is often credited with personally nurturing several firms that developed in this region, like Lockheed Martin and Hewlett- Packard. Made a popular site due to its proximity to Stanford University, for ten points, what is this region in Northern California known for headquartering many pioneering technology corporations?",
        "answer": "Silicon Valley"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A \"Mafia\" of former employees of this Peter Thiel-led company went on to found numerous tech businesses in Silicon Valley, including LinkedIn, YouTube, and Palantir.",
        "answer": [
          "PayPal",
          "PayPal Mafia"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "1992 Los Angeles Riots",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Los Angeles riots of the early 1990s, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who launched a relief effort with federal funding.",
          "answer": [
            "George H.W. Bush",
            "answers indicating the elder Bush"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Black man whose attack by policeman was caught on camera, leading to a trial which began the riots.",
          "answer": "Rodney King or Rodney Glen King"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in a nearby state which experienced looting simultaneous to LA, seven miles from a namesake \"Strip.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Las Vegas",
            "Vegas Strip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian minority whose \"Town\" was destroyed due, in part, to the killing of Latasha Harlins.",
          "answer": "Koreans"
        },
        {
          "question": "1965 riots named for an LA neighborhood to which the 1992 riots were compared due to their severity.",
          "answer": "Watts Riots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Now-controversial comedian who asked rioters to stop and watch his sitcom's finale instead.",
          "answer": [
            "Bill Cosby or William Henry Cosby Jr.",
            "The Cosby Show"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayor of LA who was accused of triggering the riots for criticizing the non-guilty brutality verdict.",
          "answer": "Tom Bradley or Thomas Bradley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conservative governor of California at the time of the riots, who requested that the Insurrection Act be invoked.",
          "answer": "Pete Wilson or Peter Barton Wilson 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Loves of Henry VIII",
      "prompt": "Concerning the wives and mistresses of the King Henry VIII of England, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First wife, the daughter of Ferdinand and Isabella.",
          "answer": "Catherine of Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only daughter he had with Anne Boleyn, known as the \"Virgin Queen.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Elizabeth I",
            "Virgin Queen before it is mentioned"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Third wife who died after giving birth to the king's only son.",
          "answer": [
            "Jane Seymour",
            "either underlined portion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Only son of Henry VIII who appointed Lady Jane Grey as his heir.",
          "answer": "Edward VI ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chief Minister who fell from power after arranging his disastrous marriage with Anne of Cleves.",
          "answer": "Thomas Cromwell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lover of Catherine Howard and friend of Henry's whose purported affair led to their executions.",
          "answer": "Thomas Culpeper"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final wife whose book Prayers or Meditations was the first published by an English queen under her own name.",
          "answer": "Catherine Parr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son by Henry's first mistress, Elizabeth Blount, who became Lord High Admiral and was considered for the throne before his death.",
          "answer": "Henry FitzRoy"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colombia",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Andean nation of Colombia, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Liberator\" of South America who served as the first President of Gran Colombia.",
          "answer": "Simón Bolívar or Simón José Antonio de la Santísima Trinidad Bolívar y Ponte Palacios y Blanco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighboring country which broke off relations following the recognition of opposition leader Juan Guaidó.",
          "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela or República Bolivariana de Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medellín [[meh-deh-YEEN]] cartel leader known as the \"King of Cocaine.\"",
          "answer": "Pablo Escobar or Pablo Emilio Escobar Gaviria"
        },
        {
          "question": "City which is named for a Spanish city founded as a \"New Carthage.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Cartagena",
            "Cartagena de Indias"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Marxist insurgent group which agreed to a truce after negotiations with Juan Manuel Santos.",
          "answer": [
            "FARC",
            "Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias de Colombia",
            "or Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Viceroyalty of the Spanish crown from which it broke away along with its neighbors.",
          "answer": [
            "Viceroyalty of New Granada or Virreinato de Nueva Granada",
            "Viceroyalty of the New Kingdom of Granada",
            "or Virreinato del Nuevo Reyno de Granada"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of domestic unrest in the 1950s, sparked by the assassination Jorge Gaitán [[\"guy\"-TAHN]].",
          "answer": "La Violencia or The Violence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late 19th century movement led by Rafael Núñez which aimed to reverse secularization.",
          "answer": [
            "La Regeneración",
            "The Regeneration 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of a rebel group in this country, Datu Amil, was killed at the Battle of Bud Bagsak, one of the final battles of a rebellion in which rebels were massacred at Bud Dajo. The Organic Act and Jones (20 pts)",
        "Act attempted to formalize a parliament in this occupied country. A president of this country was captured the Battle of Tirad Pass. This country's Moro population was suppressed with assistance from John Pershing. Manuel (10 pts)",
        "Quezon became the first president of, for ten points, what country that gained independence in the Treaty of Manila?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Philippines",
        "Republika ng Pilipinas",
        "First Philippine Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After heading the EPA, Lisa Jackson was hired by this man to improve his company’s environmental footprint. Chief Design Officer Jony Ive has reported to this man, who ascended to the CEO position after his predecessor became chairman six weeks before (20 pts)",
        "dying of pancreatic cancer in 2011. Following an attack that killed fourteen people in San Bernardino, this man’s company was asked to create custom firmware to get around the security protocols of the (10 pts)",
        "iPhone. For ten points, name this CEO of Apple since 2011."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tim Cook",
        "Timothy Donald Cook"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The so-called \"Green Count\" of Savoy and the late arrival of his five hundred men to this battle may have led to his ally's decisive defeat. The sacred banner known as the oriflamme was abandoned by its bearer at this battle, and the siege of Calais [[cah-LAY]] (20 pts)",
        "occurred in the immediate aftermath of this battle. A muddy environment slowed the charge of knights under Phillip VI at this battle, resulting in the English foot infantry and longbowmen quickly routing them. Edward the (10 pts)",
        "Black Prince orchestrated, for ten points, which early victory by the English during the Hundred Years' War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Crécy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This building was built on land purchased by the mining magnates Mott and Samuel Newhouse. The term “23 skidoo” is thought to have arisen near this building which originally did not include women’s restrooms. Originally built to serve as an office for the George A. Fuller (20 pts)",
        "Company, this Burnham-designed building now lends its name to a district of Manhattan. Found on Fifth Avenue, this building was intended to fill in a (10 pts)",
        "wedge-shaped gap at the intersection with Broadway. For ten points, name this New York skyscraper with a distinctive triangular shape."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Flatiron Building",
        "Fuller Building before mentioned 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2004, the Badeschiff [[BAH-deh-shiff]] floating swimming pool was opened on this body of water. At Eisenhüttenstadt [[\"EYE\"-zen-HOO-ten-shtaht]], formerly known as Stalinstadt, this river's Dahme [[DAH-meh]] tributary is linked to the Oder via a canal. One building along this river housed the Volkskammer (20 pts)",
        "and was torn down in 2006. That building was the Palace of the Republic which was on this river's Museum Island (10 pts)",
        "along with the Bode [[BOH-deh]] Museum. For ten points, name this tributary of the Havel river that runs through Berlin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spree River ] or Sprjewja",
        "or Spréva",
        "be lenient on pronunciation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A king of these people was forced to sign an \"Edict of Toleration\" following the arrival of Cyrille Laplace's warship, Artemise [[ahr-teh-MEESE]]. These people kept a specific breed of canine which was fed Taro root and meant to be (20 pts)",
        "consumed rather than kept as a pet. The nobility of these Marquesan Island-descended people kept same-sex lovers known as aikane, with one chief even asking James Cook to allow him to take Cook's astronomer as a partner. The (10 pts)",
        "Kamehameha family was the royal dynasty of, for ten points, which Polynesian people?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hawai'ians",
        "Marquesans before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a novel predominantly set in this state, Marie Lazarre marries her rapist, Nector, while June Morrissey freezes to death en route to a reservation. A novel set in this state that frequently references the U.S.'s entry into World War One centers on a woman who fails to work with the Jolly Seventeen (20 pts)",
        "and the Thanatopsis Club. The novel Love Medicine draws from Louise Erdrich's experiences in a Chippewa community in this state. Gopher Prarie resident Carol (10 pts)",
        "Kennicott lives in, for ten points, what state, the setting of Sinclair Lewis's Main Street?"
      ],
      "answer": "Minnesota"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Kingdom of Daʿamat was a likely indigenous state in this modern-day country that controlled cities including Matara and Qohaito. The Gash Group flourished in the neolithic period in this country, where excavations have been conducted at Sembel. The Medri (20 pts)",
        "Bahri kingdom ruled this country before its conquest by a southern neighbor, after which it fell under the control of General Oreste [[or-REST-eh]] Baratieri of the Italian Empire. (10 pts)",
        "Set free by the UNOVER referendum, for ten points, what is this Red Sea-bordering nation that gained independence from Ethiopia in 1993?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "State of Eritrea or Hagere Ertra",
        "Editor's Note: \"Da'amat\"",
        "\"D'mt\" is not to be confused with the much later Kingdom of \"Damot\" of western Ethiopia. 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ]
}